<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The ansvvere of the vicechancelour, the doctors, both the proctors, and other the heads of houses in the Vniversitie of Oxford (agreeable, vndoubtedly, to the ioint and vniforme opinion, of all the deanes and chapters, and all other the learned and obedient cleargy, in the Church of England.) To the humble petition of the ministers of the Church of England, desiring reformation of certaine ceremonies and abuses of the Church.</title>
            <author>University of Oxford.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1603</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 87 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08707</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19011</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113819</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849048</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849048</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14179</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08707)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14179)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1323:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The ansvvere of the vicechancelour, the doctors, both the proctors, and other the heads of houses in the Vniversitie of Oxford (agreeable, vndoubtedly, to the ioint and vniforme opinion, of all the deanes and chapters, and all other the learned and obedient cleargy, in the Church of England.) To the humble petition of the ministers of the Church of England, desiring reformation of certaine ceremonies and abuses of the Church.</title>
                  <author>University of Oxford.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Ioseph Barnes, and are to be sold in Paules Church-yard at the signe of the Crowne by Simon VVaterson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1603.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes the petition.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Customs and practices --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14179:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14179:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ANSVVERE OF THE VICECHAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CELOVR, THE DOCTORS, both the Proctors, and other the Heads of Houſes in the Vniverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie <hi>of Oxford:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>(Agreeable, vndoubtedly, to the ioint and Vniforme opinion, of all the Deanes and Chapters, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the learned and obedient Cleargy, in the Church of England.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the humble Petition of the Miniſters of the Church of England, deſiring Reformation of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Ceremonies and Abuſes of the Church.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Beware of the Conciſion.</hi> 
               <bibl>Philip. 3.2.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Cum ſub ſpecie ſtudij perfectionïs, imperfectionem nullam tolerare poſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, aut in Corpore, aut in membris Eccleſiae: tunc Diabolum nos tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mefacere ſuperbia, &amp; hypocriſi ſeducere, moneamur. <bibl>
                  <hi>Calvin adverſ. Anabapt. Art.</hi> 2.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>AT OXFORD,</hi> Printed by Ioſeph Barnes, and are to be ſold in <hi>Paules Church-yard at the ſigne of the Crowne by Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon VVaterſon.</hi> 1603.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14179:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14179:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE MOST REVEREND,</hi> and Right Honorable the L. Archb. of Canterbury his Grace, Primate and Metropolitane of all Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land: the L. Buchurſt, L. High Treaſurer of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and Chancelour of the Vniverſity of Oxford: the L. Cecill of Eſingden, Principall Secretarie to his Maiestie, and Chancelour of the Vniverſity of Cambridge; Lords of his Maieſties moſt Honorable Privie Counſell.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ANY and excellent were the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, which it pleaſed Almightie God to beſtowe vpon this Nation, by the Miniſtery of his choſen ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant our late Soveraigne; yet none of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were comparable vnto theſe, the Purity of Religion, perpetually ſupported by one Vniforme moſt ancient kind of commendable Church government; and the plenty of al manner of good learning, abundantly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from the two Welſprings therof, into al the parts, both of the Church and Common-wealth. For the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, both of them and the reſt, it was her wiſe and happy care, to ſelect and take neere vnto her ſucceſſiuely
<pb facs="tcp:14179:3"/> Men of rare Endowme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts &amp; perſonal gifts, men of deepe iudgment, long experience, great moderation, loving learning and fearing God. Whome therefore ſhee did place in chiefeſt authority vnder her, that vnder her they might be the greater comfort to the Miniſtery, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter encouragement vnto learning, the more noble coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance to Religion, and as the Prophet ſpeaketh<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 21.6.</note> 
               <hi>ſet as bleſsings</hi> to the whole land.</p>
            <p>In this honorable rancke we cannot, (Moſt Reverend &amp; Right Honorable) without open wrong, but acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge your Lordſhips to be ſecond vnto none of all your predeceſſours. The long experience that this kingdome hath had, of your honorable Imployments for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of Religion and learning, as your ſeverall places doe ſpeciallie require, would checke our want of duty, if wee did diſſemble it; and ſilence the detraction of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that ſhould goe about to impeach it.</p>
            <p>Which as wee recount with ſinguler comfort, for the daies that are paſt; ſo for the preſent, it is the very ſtay of our harts, that the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od, of his accuſtomed goodnes, hath given the ſame minde, vnto our moſt gracious and dread Soveraigne, to preſerue and propagate the ſame things in Church and Common-wealth, by the Godly care &amp; prudent counſaile, of the very ſelfeſame Perſons. For had we not vnder his Princely wiſedome &amp; clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, ſuch immediate Patrones, (which now with long vſe, are growne into a very ſympathy of our eſtates;) to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we might reſort in our needful times of trouble: it would amate our mindes, and vtterly aſtoniſh vs in our vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanddings, to ſee the inſolent endevours &amp; ſtraunge at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, of ſond Familiſts, abſurd Browniſts, &amp; perfidious Papiſts; all of them with importunity, and ſelfe-concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:14179:3"/> confidence, intending and expecting the innovation of Religion, through the overthrow of the Cleargy, and ruine of the Vniverſities.</p>
            <p>All which notwithſtanding, had not opened the dores of our lips, nor made way to this our iuſt complaint; but that there came to our ſight long ſince, <hi>An humble peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Thouſand Miniſters at once:</hi> Which wee may well reſemble vnto ſtill running ſtreames, which are dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt there, where they ſeeme to be moſt calme. This wee beheld with great ſorrow of heart: conſidering how it is repleate, with vnthankefulnes towards God for his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies towards vs; with iniury to <hi>Her</hi> gracious governme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, (whoſe Memory be precious vnto all poſterity;) with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to their Fathers that begot them in the Goſpell; with preiudice to the Breaſts, that (if they be any thing) did give them ſucke; with contempt of their Brethren, and fellow Laborers (at the leaſt) in the Lordes harveſt. Howbeit as long as it paſſed in private, vnder the name of a particular motion, made to his moſt excellent Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie; we l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>id our handes vpon our mouthes, and with due reverence expected in ſilence, the wiſe reſolution of His religious heart.</p>
            <p>But theſe men (as they are impatie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of delay, or els to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> gaine credite with the people, on whom they greatly do rely) ſoone after, ſend forth into al quarters of the Realm, ſtore of theſe pretended Petitions: accompanied vvith ſuch lewd, falſe, and abſurde ſuggeſtions, as if our noble King, had lent their motion a favourable eare, and given it ſome kind of conſenting intertainment; as if in all this, they had done nothing, whervnto they were not anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and encouraged, by ſome of ſpeciall credite with his Highnes; as if ſome buſie headed ſtrangers, had vnderta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb facs="tcp:14179:4"/> their cauſe, and enſured the ſafe conduit of their wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beaten barge, to the haven of their hope. Were there any ſuch, wee would requeſt them to remember, that it is neither manners nor diſcretion, to take vppon them in a <hi>State,</hi> wherein (for ought we know) they haue nothing to doe. It may ſuffice, that they are partakers of the good things of the land; let them thanke God and the King, and be quiet. But wee are verily perſwaded, there are none ſuch; that this, as all the reſt, is given out vnder hand among their credulous adherents, onely <hi>ad facien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum populum.</hi> A tricke of theirs, with which we have bin long acquainted.</p>
            <p>This courſe (Right Honorable) did make vs thinke, that nowe they had altered the nature of that foreſaide Schedule; and of an <hi>Intitled Petition to his Maieſty.</hi> Had made it a covert kind of <hi>libell.</hi> Wherby (ſecurely as they thought) they might depraue and ſlaunder, not only the Communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> booke, but the whole eſtate of the Church, as it ſtandes reformed by our late Soveraigne. VVhich vndue &amp; diſhoneſt practiſe, having ſo changed the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of their Petition; whether it hath brought the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivers and Preferrers of it within the compaſſe of that ſtatute. 1. <hi>Elizab;</hi> and made them lyable to the Penalties of the ſame: we take not vpon vs to determine. Howbeit hereof we could not but take notice; that by their impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, diverſe other very lewdly affected, haue in diverſe parts of the kingdome, preſumed to trouble his Maieſty, and taxe the ſtate, with the like clamorous <hi>libelles,</hi> and defamatory ſupplications.</p>
            <p>The conſideration whereof beganne to admoniſh vs, that now it ſorted with our duty, to ſhewe our ſelues, as truly zealous, &amp; carefully religious in the defence of the
<pb facs="tcp:14179:4"/> Church, for the quieting of mens mindes, and ſetling of their conſciences, by ſome ſhorte animadverſions vpon their proceedings: as theſe factious perſons haue beene audatiouſly venterous, &amp; praepoſteriouſly heddy, to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt their malice; thereby to diſtract and draw the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, from their loue &amp; liking of the preſent ſtate. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto wee were the rather invited, by the commendable example, of our Reverend brethren of the Vniverſitie of <hi>Cambridge;</hi> who to make knowne their diſlike of theſe &amp; ſuch like factious Schiſmatikes, haue paſſed <hi>a grace</hi> in their publicke Congregation to this effect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Placet vobis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A grace paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge Iun. 4. 1603. againſt factious Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines.</note> 
               <hi>vt quicun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> doctrinam vel diſciplinam Eccleſiae Anglicanae, vel eius partem aliquam, dictis aut ſcriptis, aut quocun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> alio modo, in Academiâ Cantabrigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſi publicè oppugnaverit: ab omni ſuſcepto gradu ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datur, &amp; à ſuſcipiendo excludatur ipſo facto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By which their wiſe and neceſſary Decree, they haue not only encouraged vs, vnto this our Apology; but with all aſſured vs, that both they themſelues, and (as we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue) many thouſands moe, of the iudicious and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Miniſters of this land: are readie to giue vs the right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand of fellowſhip in this worke, and willing to ſubſcribe vnto the ſame, if the cauſe did neceſſarily require it, or the time would permitte.</p>
            <p>But your Lordſhips know right well, that Truth ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth no great auctoritie, by the many voices that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it at once. And for our parts we vtterly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the courſe, that theſe Schiſmatikes have therein taken. Who to bolſter out their ſtale obiections and falſe calumniatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, have trudged vp &amp; downe diverſe Shires, to get the conſent, of they care not whom; ſo they may make vp the tale, and pretend a number. In which kind,
<pb facs="tcp:14179:5"/> that was a notable Stratageme which (farre beſides the Authors purpoſe) we did light vpon of late. May it pleaſe your Lordſhips to haue patience, while wee propoſe it, and ſo leaue it to your Honorable cenſure.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>H. I.</hi> a man that was of ordinarie partes, &amp; of as or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary place, when he lived among vs; is now, it ſeemes, become a principall Agent, and a ſpeciall Procurator of the publicke cauſe among the factious. He, (much miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in his ſtrong conceipt, that to inſinuate with a man of wiſedome, woulde bee ſufficient to fetch him over to that ſide.) Writes vnto one of eminent ſorte among vs, after this faſhion.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>MOreover I am to let you vndersta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, that many lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and godly Miniſters,<note n="a" place="margin">Scilicet in Iune, when their Petition was Exhibited in April before</note> 
                     <hi>are about to exhibite</hi> to the Kings Maieſtie, a Petition for the Reformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of things amiſſe in our Church; wherevnto a conſent of as many, as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>veniently we can get, is very behooueful. My opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; truſt is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning you, that you will be, not only a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker, but alſo a furtherer of this Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> duty. I have ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t you here incloſed the <hi>forme to be ſubſcribed,</hi> by all ſuch, as have good will to this purpoſe I pray you let me have an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere hereof from you, as ſoone as you may; vvith ſo manie of your well affected friendes handes therevnto, as ſhall bee <hi>(thought)</hi> good. It is not intended that your names ſhall bee raſhly ſhewed, to any mans preiudice, but be reſerved to a fit opportunity; if we ſhall perceive, that they altogither being brought forth, will further our deſires &amp; ſuite. Of the good ſucceſſe whereof, we conceave good hope, thanks be to God. Thus beſeeching God to keepe and ſanctifie vs for his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and to give vs vviſedome in all thinges: Ibid
<pb facs="tcp:14179:5"/> you hartely farewell. VVoodſtreete in London the XXX. of Iune. <hi>1603.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours to his power H. I.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <postscript>
                     <p>Post ſcript. I could wiſh you to conferre with D. A. about this matter.</p>
                  </postscript>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Thus much of the Letter.</p>
            <p>Now the Forme to be ſubſcribed vnto, is this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVe whoſe names are vnder written doe agree to make our humble Petition to the Kinges Maieſtie, that the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent state of the Church, may bee farther reformed in all things needefull; according to the rule of Gods holy worde, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd agreeable to the example of other reformed Churches, which haue reſtored both the Doctrine &amp; Diſcipline, as it was delivered by our Saviour Chriſt, and his holy Apoſtles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your Lordſhips ſee the manner of the men. This col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion and coven, were very baſe betweene man &amp; man. But for them, thus to vſe their Soveraigne; firſt to give him a Petition in the name of a Thouſande, and then to ſcatter it abroad with this gloſſe,, <hi>Of the good ſucceſſe of our ſuite, we do conceaue good hope: thanks be to God;</hi> Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <hi>ex poſt facto,</hi> to begge and ſteale as many hands to it, as could be got: this is <hi>ſuch stuffe,</hi> as wee will paſſe over with reference to that of <hi>Tully</hi> vnto <hi>Antonie;</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Philip. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Tu autem eò liberior, &amp;c.</hi> It is the advantage ſome Men have, that they dare to do ſuch things, as a modeſt Adverſarie can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not well reprove. But it is ſuteable to the Imputations they have laide vpon their late Princes governement. And now alſo, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his Maieſty ſhall fruſtrate their vaine
<pb facs="tcp:14179:6"/> imaginations; they have lefte their olde wont, if ſome of them doe not verifie that of the Poet,
<q>
                  <l>— Fermentum, &amp; quae ſemelintùs</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Perſ: Satyr. 1.</note>Innata eſt, rupto iecore, exibit Caprificus.</l>
               </q> Howſoever; the Thing that we would ſpecially obſerue out of this Script; is in the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner of <hi>Subſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Where hence it doth moſt plainely appeare, that the particulars ſpecified in the Petition; are not the vtmoſt End whereat they aime; they haue another marke.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>"All thinges needefull according to the rule of Gods VVord &amp; agreable to the example of other reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches;</hi> is their Vp-ſhot. But is it ſo indeede? Why, They of the Petition <hi>deſire</hi> (onely) <hi>Reformation of certaine Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies and Abuſes: They neither as factious men, affect a Popular Paritie in the Church, nor as Schiſmatickes, aime at the diſsolution of the State Eccleſiasticall: their humble ſuite is, that the offences follovving may bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, amended, qualified: They</hi> (good men) <hi>deſire That vvhich ſhall be preiudiciall vnto none, but &amp;c.</hi> It is true; The voice of the Petition, might ſeeme to be the voice of <hi>Iacob,</hi> though the hands of the Subſcription appeare plainely to be the hands of <hi>Eſau;</hi> were it not that there is alſo a Clauſe in their Petition. (Now that we have their owne expoſition of it, we can obſerve it; and, that it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated thrice for failing, viz. <hi>Theſe and ſome other vſed; Theſe and other ſuch like; Theſe vvith other ſuch Abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes;</hi>) which houldeth very good correſponde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy with the forme of Subſcription. Heeretofore, we could not tell what to make of thoſe wordes, and therefore made them no anſwere. They ſeemed vnto vs a very <hi>Nemo Scit;</hi> a Mathematike Line, <hi>diuiſibilis in ſemper deviſibilia:</hi> but now vpon this new Advertiſement, having co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb facs="tcp:14179:6"/> we finde them Paralele, to thoſe <hi>All things needfull &amp;c.</hi> in the Subſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Which tell vs plainly, They wil never have an end, till either they have ſet vp the Presbitery, Or elſe be cut of by Authority.</p>
            <p>The third &amp; laſt remarkeable matter, which we hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> referre vnto your Lordſhips due regard, is a certeine Semblance, which in this our halfe yeares ſilence, vvee haue obſerved in two contrary Factions, that haue ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelues by their Petitions, diſcontented with the praeſent State, &amp; Eccleſiaſticall Government: namely in the <hi>Papiſts</hi> and the <hi>Puritants.</hi> VVe will vſe their owne ſtyle, and come as neere as we can, to their very words.</p>
            <p n="1">1 They Both intitle themſelues the Kinges <hi>afflicted ſubiectes,</hi> and aboue all other, <hi>his devoted ſervants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 They Both pretend <hi>an enforcement of a ſpeedy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to his Maiestie, for a preſent Redreſſe and Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 They Both co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaine, of being overwhelmed with <hi>enduring perſecution through loſſe of Living &amp; Liberty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 They Both ground their Doctrine and Diſcipline vpon the <hi>ſacred text of Gods word and Goſpell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5 They Both condemne the obedience of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantes to the Lawes Eſtabliſhed, to bee, not for Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and zeale: but for <hi>Morall honeſtie, and feare of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall puniſhment,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Papist; For their owne quiet, credit, and profit in the world,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Puritaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6 They Both renou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce <hi>a publicke alteratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; diſsolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the State Eccleſiaſt.</hi> but the one pleads for <hi>a private Toleration,</hi> the other (forſooth) <hi>for a Godly Reformation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7 They Both deny that they exhibite their Petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, with <hi>a tumultuous ſpirit, or with a diſloyall &amp; Schiſmatical minde.</hi> Of vvhich their Semblable Aſſertions, in argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb facs="tcp:14179:7"/> ſo oppoſite, we might ſay in a word, as the <hi>Orator</hi> doth of contrarie Opinions; <hi>It cannot be that more then one of them ſhould poſsiblie bee true, but it is very poſsible, that both may bee falſe.</hi> Yet we rather take vp that in the Booke of<note n="*" place="margin">Iud. 15.4.</note> 
               <hi>Iudges,</hi> and ſay of them and their deſignes:</p>
            <p>Verily theſe men are like <hi>Samſons Foxes.</hi> They have <hi>their heades ſevered</hi> indeed; the One ſort looking to the <hi>Papacy,</hi> the Other to the <hi>Presbiterie.</hi> But they <hi>are tyed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither by the tailes, vvith fire brandes betvveene them.</hi> Which if they bee not quenched in time, are able to ſet the whole Land in a Combuſtion and Vprore.</p>
            <p>IF in any of theſe, or in them all, there do appeare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Lordſhips ſuch matter of moment, as might move men of care, &amp; ſome diſcretion to write in defence of themſelues, and the preſent State; if in our manner of writing, wee haue held that hand, (not by way of large diſcourſe, but as the brevity of Notes will ſuffer,) which doth beſeeme a modeſt and ingenuous anſwere; if in nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them there be any thing ſo offenſiue, or defectiue, or impertinent, but that, vnder the winges of your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Patronage it may paſſe into the Preſence of his Excellent Maieſtie, and there attend his moſt iudicious and learned Cenſure, yet ſo attempered with his rare &amp; ſinguler mildnes, as in it he is wont to accept the duty &amp; ſervice of his meaner Subiects: <hi>then</hi> (and not otherwiſe) we beſeech your Lordſhips that of your wonted favour, you will accompany it with your gracefull Preſence, and as the Argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of our religious Affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in al humility preſent it to his Highnes: <hi>then</hi> wee entreate, that in the Honorable regard you have of thoſe <hi>Noble partes</hi> of this Church, which God hath ſpecially betaken into your Protectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; in the loyal remembrance you retaine of Her
<pb facs="tcp:14179:7"/> Maieſtie that late was, and her happie Government; in the bounden dutie you owe to his Maieſtie that nowe is, and the Well doing of his whole Kingdome; in the Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and zeale which you beare to God, his Church, and to his ſacred truth: you will take occaſion <hi>heereby,</hi> All as one man, ioyntly to imploy that great Grace, and high Favour, which God hath given you in the eies of your Soveraigne; to the preſent ſupporte of Religion, maintenaunce of Learning, defence of the Church, ſtrengthening the State, ſetling the mindes of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, eſtabliſhing peace and tranquillitie in the Land: by taking the <hi>Foxes,</hi> the little <hi>Foxes,</hi> vvhich marre our Vines, that they beare ſmall Grapes; and by chaſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the wilde <hi>Boare</hi> of the Wood, and the <hi>Beaſtes</hi> of the Forreſt; that otherwiſe would eate them vp, and vtterly deſtroy them. So God ſhall take Pleaſure in your Care and Conſcience; the King in your faithfull Service; his Subiects ſhal dwel ſafe, vnder the ſhadow of his Wings; and we your Clients ſhall ſend this teſtimony after you: Many Patrones of the Clergie, many Chauncelours of the Vniverſities, <hi>have done vertuouſly, but Theſe ſurmou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the God that giveth both Glorie, and Grace, give your Lordſhips all manner of Graces fitte for your High Callings in this World; and That farre moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and eternall waight of Glorie, in the World to come.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips in all dutie, <hi>The Vicechancelour, the Doctors, the Proctors, and other the Heades of Houſes in the Vniverſitie of Oxford.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:14179:8"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Mmediately after the Printing of our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to the Petition, there came vnto vs, a very kinde and wel-penned Letter, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this matter. Which wee might not ſuppreſſe, (though it bee but rudely here inſerted) without great iniury, to that whole Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity; and no leſſe detriment vnto the cauſe it ſelfe.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>JNDORSED</hi> To the Vicechancelour, and others of the Vniverſity of Oxford.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Vm nuperrimè, &amp; quidem ſerò ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum, ad aures nostras perveniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet fama de <hi>libello</hi> Regiae Maieſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti pro reformandà (ſcilicet) Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſià à <hi>Miniſtris mille,</hi> vt perhiben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, exhibito: et ſi nihil in eo novi reperiretur, cui non plus millies an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tehàc reſponſum ſit, tamèn quoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am numerum iactant, vt intelligerent <hi>Millenarij iſti,</hi> Si Saulo mille adſtent, Davidi in hac cauſa decies mille nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam de futuros; nihil prius habuimus, aut antiquius, quam vt <hi>Operi</hi> omni reſponſione indigniſsimo, aliquod tamen re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponſum pararemus. Quod dum meditamur, defertur ad nos Academiae Oxonienſis Apologia certè diſertiſsima, quae rationum momentis breviſsimè refutaret, quicquid <hi>ab Iſtis</hi> tanto anteà labore confectum eſſet, aut confictum.
<pb facs="tcp:14179:8"/> Qua conſpecta, nihil nobis reliqui videbatur, quos ita an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teverterat Fratru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> noſtrorum in cauſa optima zelus &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtria prompta ſatis &amp; parata ad hominum leviſsimorum ictus omnes vel ex tempore refellendos: quàm cum illi pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere certaſſent argumentorum, nos numero, quo <hi>Iſti</hi> maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me gloriantur, pugnaremus. Quod &amp; anteà, quaſi divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantes &amp; praevidimus, &amp; providimus. Cum enim defun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta <hi>Elizabetha</hi> Regina optima, &amp; in cauſa optima, (quod in muliere prope ſingulare eſt, &amp; inauditum) ſemper conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſsimâ, ſemper eâdem, non tam Principis Religioſiſſimae interitum, &amp; religionis ſi non intereuntis, at ſummè certè periclitantis caſum deplorare, quam in adventum Regis no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi novas res meditari <hi>Iſti</hi> caepiſſent &amp; in dies moliri: per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opportunè ſuccurrendum cenſuit Academia, &amp; convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſenatu frequenti admodum, &amp; celebri decernendum; vt <hi>Quicun<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Eccleſiae Anglicanae doctrinam, vel Diſcipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam, vel ejus partem aliquam legibus publicis ſtabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam, ſcriptis, vel dictis, vel quocun<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> modo, in Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia Cantabrigienſi publicè oppugnaverit, ab omni gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>du ſuſcipiendo excludatur, &amp; à ſuſcepto ſuſpendatur ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo facto.</hi> Quod quidem Decretum concenſu propè vnanimi comprobatum, &amp; tabulis publicis Iunij<note n="*" place="margin">Our pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was, as if it had bin decreed the 4. of Iune.</note> 
                     <hi>9. 1603.</hi> conſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, nunc demum teſtatum cupimus vniverſis, vt intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant omnes de Diſciplina nostra, non impoſita, ſed ſuſcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta liberè &amp; retenta quid exiſtiment, non in angulis <hi>Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtri nonnulli,</hi> ſed in aperto Senatu Cantabrigienſes propè vniverſi. Quorum conſenſus, cum tam fraternè concinat &amp; conſpiret cum Apologia Oxonienſi, cum Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turis, Patribus, Concilijs, Principum noſtrorum Decretis, Legibus, Parliamentis; eant nunc <hi>mille Iſti,</hi> &amp; libris no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris fere mille in hunc finem editis &amp; conſcriptis cum erit otium &amp; facultas, reſpondeant prius, quàm Cramben toties
<pb facs="tcp:14179:9"/> decoctam Regitam prudenti, tam literato, tam impudenter obtrudant. Aut ſi numerari malint quam ponderari ſuffra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia, cogitent <hi>homunciones miſeri,</hi> ab Academijs Muſiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> relicti, quam nullius numeri ſint, quam planè nihili. Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lete fratres in Chriſto Chariſſimi, &amp; nos noſtram<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miam ſumma vobis &amp; ſtudiorum &amp; morum ſimilitudine coniunctiſſima<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vt facitis, amate. Cantab. Octob. <hi>7. 1603.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>SVBSCRIBED <hi>By the Vice chancelour, and others the Heades of the Vniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Cambridge.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14179:9"/>
            <head>THE HVMBLE PETITION OF <hi>THE MJNJSTERS OF THE Church of England, deſiring Reformation of certaine Ceremonies and abuſes of the Church.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">To the moſt Chriſtian and excellent PRINCE, our Gracious and dread Soveraigne, IAMES <hi>by the grace of God &amp;c.</hi> Wee the Miniſters of the Church of England that deſire Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; vviſh a long proſperous and happie Raigne over vs, in this life, and in the next everlaſting ſalvation.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OST gracious &amp; dread Soveraigne, ſeeing it hath pleaſed the devine Maiestie, to the great comfort of all good Chriſtians, to advaunce your Highnes, according to your iuſt title, to the peaceable goverment of this Church and Common wealth of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land: we the Miniſters of the Goſpell in this land, neither as factious men, affecting a popular Paritie in the Church, nor as Schiſmatikes ayming at the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14179:10"/> diſſolution of the ſtate Eccleſiaſticall: but as the faithfull ſervants of Chriſt, and loyall ſubiectes to your Maiesty, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring and longing for the redreſſe of diverſe abuſes of the Church; could doe no leſſe, in our obedience to God, ſervice to your Maieſtie, love to his Church: then acquainte your Princely Maieſtie, vvith our particular griefes. For as your Princely penne writeth, <hi>The King as a good Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, muſt firſt know what peccant humors his pacient na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally is moſt ſubiect vnto, before he can begin his cure:</hi> And although divers of vs that ſue for Reformation, have formerly in reſpect of the times ſubſcribed to the booke, ſome vpon Proteſtatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſome vpon expoſitions given them, ſome with condition, rather then the Church ſhoulde haue beene deprived of theie labour and Ministery: yet now we, to the number of more then a thouſand, of your Maiesties ſubiectes and Ministers, all groaning as vnder a common burden of humane Rites and Ceremonies, do with one ioint conſent humble our ſelues at your Maiesties feete, to be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and relieved in this behalfe. Our humble ſuite then vnto your Maieſtie is, that theſe offences, following, ſome may be removed, ſome amended, ſome qualified.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1 In the Church ſervice.</hi> That the Croſſe in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, interrogatories miniſtred to Infants, Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmation, as ſuperfluous may bee taken away Baptiſme not to bee mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred by VVomen, and ſo explaned. The Cap and Surplice not vrged. That examination may goe before the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. That it bee miniſtred with a Sermon. That diverſe termes of <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>Abſolution,</hi> and ſome other vſed, with the <hi>Ring in mariage,</hi> &amp; other ſuch like in the booke, may be corrected. The long ſomenes of ſervice abridged. Church ſongs and Muſicke moderated to better edification. That the Lords day be not prophaned. The reſt vpon Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daies
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14179:10"/> not ſo ſtrictly vrged. That there may bee an vnifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of doctrine preſcribed. No popiſh opinion to be any more taught or defended. No Miniſters Charged to teach their people to bow at the name of Ieſus. That the Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Scriptures onely be read in the Church.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2 Concerning Church Miniſters.</hi> That none here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after be admitted into the Miniſtery, but able and ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent men, and thoſe, to preach diligently; and eſpecially vpon the Lords day. That ſuch as bee already entred and cannot preach, may either be removed, and ſome charitable courſe taken with them for their reliefe: or elſe to be forced ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the valew of their livings, to mainetaine prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers. That Non-reſidencie be not permitted. That King <hi>Edwards</hi> statute for the lawfulnes of Miniſters mariage, be revived. That Miniſters be not vrged to ſubſcribe, but, according to the Law, to the Articles of Religion, and the Kings ſupremacy onely.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3 For Church livings and maintenance.</hi> That Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops leave their Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendams: ſome holding Prebends, ſome Parſonages, ſome Vicarages with their Biſhoprickes. That double beneficed men, be not ſuffered to hold, ſome two, ſome three benefices with cure and ſome two three, or foure dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities beſides. That Impropriatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s annexed to Biſhoprickes and Colledges, be demiſed only to the Preachers Incumbe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, for the old Rent. That the Impropriations of Lay mens fee, may be charged with a ſixt, or ſeaventh part of the worth, to the maintenance of the preaching Minister.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4 For Church Diſcipline.</hi> That the Diſcipline, and Excommunicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may be adminiſtred according to Chriſts ovvne inſtitution. Or at the leaſt, that enormities may bee redreſſed. As namelie, That Excommunication come not forth vnder the name of Lay perſons, Chauncellours, Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cials
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14179:11"/> &amp;c. That men be not excommunicated for trifles and twelue-penny matters. That none be exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municated with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out conſent of his Pastor. That the officers be not ſuffered to extort vnreaſonable fees. That none having iuriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Regiſter places, put out the ſame to farme. That di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Popiſh Canons, (as for reſtraint of marriage at cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine times) be reverſed. That the Long-ſomnes of ſuites in Eccleſiaſticall courts, (which hang ſometime two, three, foure, five, ſixe or ſeaven yeares) may be reſtrained. That the Oth <hi>ex officio,</hi> wherby men are forced to accuſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues bee more ſparingly vſed. That Licenſes for mariage without Banes asked, be more cautiouſly granted.</p>
            <p>Theſe with ſuch other Abuſes yet remaining &amp; practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the Church of England, we are able to ſhew, not to be agreeable to the Scriptures, if it ſhall pleaſe your Highnes farther to heare vs, or more at large by writing to be enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, or by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ference among the learned to be reſolved. And yet we doubt not, but that vvithout anie farther proceſſe, your Maieſty (of whoſe Christian iudgement we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived ſo good a taſt alreadie) is able of your ſelfe, to iudge of the equity of this cauſe. God we trust hath appointed your Highnes our Phyſition, to heale theſe diſeaſes. And we ſay with <hi>Mordecai</hi> to <hi>Heſter, who knoweth; whether you are come to the kingdome for ſuch a time?</hi> Thus your Maieſty ſhall do that, which we are perſwaded, ſhall be acceptable to God, honorable to your Maieſtie in all ſucceeding ages, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to his Church which ſhall be thereby encreaſed, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable to your Miniſters, which ſhall be no more ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, ſilenced, diſgraced, impriſoned for mens Traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: &amp; preiudiciall to none, but to thoſe that ſeeke their owne qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, credit, and profit in the world. Thus vvith all dutifull ſubmiſsion, referring our ſelves to your Maiesties plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14179:11"/> for your gracious anſwere, as God ſhall direct you: wee moſt humbly recommend your Highnes to the divine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty; whome wee beſeech for Chriſt his ſake to diſpoſe your royall heart to doe heerein, what ſhal be to his glory, the good of his Church, and your endles comfort.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Maieſties moſt humble Subiects,</hi> The Miniſters of the Gospell, that deſire not a diſorderly innovation, but a due and godlie Reformation.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:14179:12"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE ANSWERE OF THE VICE</hi>-CHAVNCELOVR, THE DOC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, both the Proctors, &amp; other the Heads of Houſes in the Vniverſity of Oxford, <hi>To the Petition of the Miniſters of the Church of England deſiring Reformation.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <head>In their Petition, there are three principall partes.</head>
               <item>1 A Preface.</item>
               <item>2 A Conplaint conſiſting of fowre ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all pointes; In everie of them the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that certaine Ceremonies and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes, may bee ſome of them removed, ſome amended, ſome qualified.</item>
               <item>3 A Concluſion.</item>
            </list>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>FOR ANSWERE WHEREVNTO:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14179:12"/> 
                  <hi>1</hi> In Generall.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>EE moſt humbly beſeech his moſt excellent Maieſtie, that it may bee conſidered, how inconvenient and vnſufferable it is in Chriſtian poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, to permit a long and well ſetled ſtate of government, to be ſo much as queſtioned; much more to bee<note n="a" place="margin">Ipſa mutatio conſuetudinis etiam quae ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuvat vtilitate, novitate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbat Auguſt ad Ianuar. Ep. 118 cap. 5.</note> altered, for a few of his Subiects: eſpecially conſidering the matter, pretended to bee the cauſe of theſe mens griefe, and of their deſired Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, vniuſtly ſo called. For it is either the <hi>Ceremonies</hi> of the Church, or <hi>Abuſes</hi> in the Church, as they alleadge. Wherein wee humbly recommende to his Princely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance.</p>
               <p>Firſt concerning Ceremonies, that they are either ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious; &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no waies to be admitted. Of which ſort it ſhould ſeeme by the Petitioners, (and we are ready to proue) that the Ceremonies of our Church are not. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe theſe men co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe, that in reſpect of the times they did ſubſcribe vnto them: or if they were ſuch, with what conſcience did they ſubſcribe, in reſpect of the times?</p>
               <p>Or els, things in themſelues indifferent. And then the ſupreme Chriſtian Magiſtrate, hath lawfull<note n="b" place="margin">Melan. in 13. ad Rom. Pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mortale eſt violate edi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cta Magiſtrat. &amp;c. Heming. in Syntag ca de Adiaph Qui vi olat Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticam politia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peccat multis modis, &amp;c. Bez. Epiſt 24. ad artic. 7.</note> authoritie to forbid, and we muſt forbeare: to commande, and wee muſt obey; not only for feare, but for conſcience ſake. Of which kinde if theſe Ceremonies be (as wee will iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, and they cannot deny) where is then their pretended obedience? Where is their applauſe of his Maieſties peaceable government? Why doe they trouble both Church &amp; Common wealth, in reſpect of matters which in duty and conſcience they may wel, and ought willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to ſubmit themſelues vnto?</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:14179:13"/>
               <p>Secondly concerning Abuſes, be it conſidered: firſt of what qualitie they are; ſecondly of what degree.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Touching the nature or quality of them, whether they are in the very Conſtitutions of our Church, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Execution of the ſaid Conſtitutions. If not in the Conſtitutions themſelues, (as when we deſcende to the particulars it wil appeare:) there is no cauſe why the government ſhould be changed; or theſe men ſuffered, thus to calumniate the State, wherein there is nothing <hi>Poſitiue,</hi> that is worthy of blame. If in the Execution; (which as we wil not abſolutely deny, ſo theſe men can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not eaſily proue,) that may be remedied by amending or removing of ſome certaine offendors, without alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſtate.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Touching the degree or grievouſnes of theſe abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, (whether in the Conſtitution, as they ſuppoſe, &amp; we deny; or in the Execution, vvhich ſimply and in every particular,<note n="c" place="margin">Calv. adv. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ab. art. a. V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> (ſc. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ari &amp; Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtae) in eode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rrore fueru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, Quo iſti ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iatores; Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>leſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quaere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s in qua ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>il poſſet deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rari, &amp;c.</note> no Church in Chriſtendome is able to iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, and yet none, ſo much as this of ours:) we vndertake to proue againſt the Thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, that maſke vnknowne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that generalitie, that they are not ſuch, nor ſo hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous, as deſerue this their bitter reprehenſion: much leſſe ſuch an alteration, in the Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, as would enſue; if theſe Petitioners might haue their deſire.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>2.</hi> In Particular. <hi>Concerning the Preface.</hi> VVe doe but note.</head>
               <p n="1">1 WHAT reckoning (in truth) theſe men doe make, of <hi>iuſt titles vnto kingdomes,</hi> vvho fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14179:13"/> them<note n="d" place="margin">De lur. reg apud Scot. De lur Magiſt in ſubd: Vind cont tyr. Hotto. Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cog.</note> to much, that were wont to ſubiect all kings titles vnto popular election and approbation.</p>
               <p n="2">2 What comfort (in deede) the Petitioners take in the <hi>peace of his Maieſties government;</hi> who in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry entrance thereof, by ſeeking this and the like daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous alterations, doe diſquiet &amp; diſturbe the ſame. Were other men as litle inured to peace &amp; ſubiection, it might occaſion ſome inconvenience.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Howſoever in wordes they decline the imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>of factious men affecting popular parity in the Church, &amp;, of Schiſmatikes ayming at the diſſolution of the State Eccleſiaſticall:</hi> yet it is to well knowen in this kingdome, and by experience it hath bin felte in that of<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. pag. 39, 40, 41, &amp;c.</note> Scotland, what manner of men they be: as alſo, what haue bin the lamentable effects of their reformations there, &amp; would haue bin likewiſe heere, had not the prudent fore-ſight, and conſtant reſolution of our late gracious Soveraigne, continually repreſſed their attemptes.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Theſe men might haue performed better, <hi>Their obedience to God, their ſervice to his Maieſtie, their love to his Church:</hi> (as in the particulars will appeare) if they had forborne to trouble his Maieſty, the church of God, &amp; this common-wealth, with theſe their cauſeles griefs and diſcontentments. They haue thereby made ſuch a breach as will not eaſily (without much wiſedome &amp; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience) bee cured. For what are theſe men, that they ſhould aſſume ſo much for what are the whole Cleargy of England beſides, that they ſhould bee ſo abaſed and contemned?</p>
               <p n="5">5 That which they alleage out of his Highnes <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, is a childiſh fallacie; abſurdly taking that for granted, which is the maine queſtion. They muſt proue
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14179:14"/> (and not aſſume,) that theſe are the <hi>peccant humours of this Church,</hi> which in trueth is the<note n="f" place="margin">Iuel. Apo. 170. Acceſſimus quantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè potuimus ad Eccleſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſt &amp;c. Et 46. Ea om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia quae aut lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ola &amp;c. Aut cum lacris literis pugna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia aut etiam ſobrijs homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> indigna &amp;c. prorſus ſine vl la exceptione repudia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>imus.</note> leaſt <hi>peccant</hi> of any in the world, and would be much leſſe <hi>peccant,</hi> if it were cleane purged, of theſe vnquiet and malecontented hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours.</p>
               <p n="6">6 That <hi>diverſe of them have formerly ſubſcribed to the booke,</hi> (as skornfully they tearme it) doth manifeſtly evince, that either our <hi>Leiturgy</hi> is iuſtifiable, themſelues being Iudges; or els that they did liberally diſpence with their owne conſciences, which is not the parte of honeſt men. To do that <hi>in reſpect of the times,</hi> which in it ſelfe is not lawful, proveth litle leſſe then hypocriſie: to alleadge vnknowne <hi>Proteſtations, Expoſitions, and Conditions</hi> in their ſubſcription, doth argue no ſincerity; and vpon due examination, will fall out to be nothing, but meere fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie.</p>
               <p n="7">7 As for their <hi>labours in the Ministery</hi> be they ſuch as they are. This Church of England had beene happy if it had not beene troubled, with their factions ſermons &amp;<note n="g" place="margin">Mart. Mar. P. Miles monop. Hay any work &amp; the reſt of that ſpirit.</note> ſcurrile Pamphlets: which have given the Adverſary, much matter of advantage, diſtracted the minds of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny weake ones, and quite turned ſome other from the loue of the Truth.</p>
               <p n="8">8 The number of <hi>more then a Thouſand,</hi> is but a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, which we humbly intreat, may be pul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed from their faces, that we may ſee and know the men, that thus <hi>grone</hi> vnder the yoke of a Chriſtian &amp; commendable governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; which (maliciouſly and iniuriouſly) they woulde have reputed, <hi>a moſt heavy burden of humane Rites &amp; Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies.</hi> The vanity of which their complaint, comes now more particularly to be diſcuſſed.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:14179:14"/>
                  <head>Concerning the matters of their Complaint: 1. <hi>Of Church ſervice.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1 IN the Church ſervice, we are ready to mainetaine, (but they muſt obiect firſt and proue the contrary.) That the <hi>Croſſe in Baptiſme, Interrogatories mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred to Infants, and Confirmation,</hi> are moſt ancient, iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiable, and convenient Ceremonies, and therefore to be continued.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 That the Church of England, nor the booke of Common praier doth not preſcribe, that <hi>Baptiſme ſhould be adminiſtred by women.</hi> Though we deny it not, to bee<note n="h" place="margin">Chytrae. de Bap. &amp; in Lev. Sneph. de Bap. Zuingl de Bap. Hierbr. in Comp. Theol.</note> Baptiſme, if perchance <hi>de facto,</hi> it bee by them admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred. <hi>Fieri non debuit, factum valuit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3 That the <hi>Cap and Surplice be not vrged,</hi> it is an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurde ſpeach and implyes confuſion. For ſo every man ſhould be ſuffered in that behalfe to doe what him liketh. Againe, do not their owne words import, that they may well be vſed? but they muſt not be <hi>vrged.</hi> Why? what is there in a Cap or in a Surplice, that ſhould<note n="i" place="margin">Buc. de re veſt pag. 707. Pet Mart. Ep. ad Hop. Aug. Ep. 154. Calv. in Ex. 23</note> offende any man of iudgement?</p>
                  <p n="4">4 That <hi>Examination</hi> where neede is, ſhould <hi>goe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> who diſliketh? Or that it <hi>be miniſtred with a ſermon?</hi> But that it ſhould not be miniſtred vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a ſermon, is abſurd; and hath bred in many a vaine and falſe opinion, as if, not the worde of Chriſts Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but rather the word of a Miniſters expoſition, were a<note n="k" place="margin">T. C. lib. 1. pag. 158.</note> neceſſarily and an eſſentiall part of the Communion. Beſides he that readeth our Communion booke, ſhall ſee that therein the whole manner, end, and vſe of that holy inſtitution, is ſo excellently deſcribed, as may be inſteede of many ſermons. Alſo that none ſhould be admitted to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14179:15"/> that bleſſed Sacrament, (of what age, ſtate, or condition ſo ever) except they were firſt examined after the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtorian faſhion, were inſolent, iniurious, &amp; in many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects moſt inconvenient.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 The termes of<note n="l" place="margin">Iſai 66 21. Where the Geneva note doth ſhewe, that the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the new teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t are to be tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Prieſts.</note> 
                     <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Abſolution: the</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Bucer in Ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ſur. cap. 10.</note> 
                     <hi>Ring in Marriage and ſuch other,</hi> which they haue heretofore traduced in their vnlearned diſcourſes; are by diverſe of our learned Devines, and ſhalbee iuſtified. As contrary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by the Petitioners they wil neuer be evicted worthy to be aboliſhed.</p>
                  <p n="6">6 Their deſire <hi>to haue the long-ſomnes of ſervice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridged,</hi> doth well befit their great Devotion. Who not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding are wont to ſpende an houre ſometimes or little leſſe, in extemporarie, inconſequent, and ſenſleſſe praiers conceived raſhly by themſelues. From hence, their diſlike of ſet &amp; ſtinted formes of praier, it doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede, that ſome of them omit, ſome refuſe to repeate, ſome condemne the vſe of the Lords praier; from hence hath <hi>Barrow</hi> and <hi>Greene wood</hi> taken their beginning, and fetched the premiſſes of their peſtilent and blaſphemous Concluſions.</p>
                  <p n="7">7 <hi>Church</hi>
                     <note n="m" place="margin">Iuſt Mart in quaeſt ad Or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h q. 107. Aug Conf. li. 10. cap 33.</note> 
                     <hi>ſongs and Muſicke,</hi> are much beholden to theſe men now: in as much as they can be content to diſgeſt them, ſo they <hi>bee moderated to better edification.</hi> The time was when wee haue heard them ſpeake in this point, after another ſort. <hi>Meretricious Church-Muſicke, Toſsing of tennis bals,</hi> and ſuch like; were there phraſes of Gods devine ſervice. But thanked bee God, that his Maieſties devout affection in this kind, hath forced from them this moderation.</p>
                  <p n="8">8 <hi>That the Lords day be not prophaned,</hi> hee is verie prophane that deſireth not from his hart. But what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14179:15"/> of law-givers are they, that lay downe their conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in ſuch Negatiues, in ſuch Comparatiues? For who can devine what they would haue, when they deſire <hi>that the Reſt vpon</hi>
                     <note n="n" place="margin">Pet Martyr. Epiſt. ad Hop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perum.</note> 
                     <hi>Holy daies be not ſo ſtrictly vrged?</hi> Would they haue men vpon ſuch daies goe to plough and carte, as ſome of their humor haue cauſed their ſervants to do, on the very feaſt of Chriſts Nativity? Or do they meane, that we ſhould take to our ſelues ſuch liberty therein, as certaine Perſons lately haue done; who being comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by lawfull auctority to celebrate the fifte of Auguſt, with ioy and thankſgiving for his Maieſties moſt ſtrange and wonderful deliverance, vpon the ſaid day now three yeares paſt; did notwithſtanding ſpende the ſame (as wee are credibly informed) in faſting and mourning and ſuch like workes of their obedience? Nay theſe &amp; the like ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments doe cauſe vs, humbly and inſtantly to deſire, that both Sundaies and Holydaies may bee religiouſly obſerved; and the intollerable prophanation of them, which is the rather brought in, by theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s preachings and examples may be very ſeverely puniſhed.</p>
                  <p n="9">9 <hi>That there may be an Vniformity of Doctrine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed. That no Popiſh opinions may be any more taught or defended?</hi> What imputations are theſe? howe preiudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all? How iniurious? Not only vnto the Church governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but vnto the Chriſtian faith eſtabliſhed in this Realme? What advantage do theſe men in theſe ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſuggeſtions reach vnto the Papiſts? As if there were no<note n="o" place="margin">We refer to the Articles of Religion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed vpon &amp; eſtabliſhed in Convocation. Anno 1562.</note> vniformity, no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent of doctrin amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vs? (ſo ye ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.) As if there were ſome Popiſh opinions taught and defended in our Leiturgy? (as they deeme who are ready to make every thing<note n="p" place="margin">Zanch. conf. cap 24 de Ec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l. Milit. Aph. 19.</note> Popery which they doe not fancy) Theſe are the weapons with which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> &amp;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14179:16"/> that broode, are wont to wounde, or rather falſely to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach our faith and profeſſion. Good had it beene that theſe men had never beene able to write, rather then to write thus, to the ſcandall of Gods Church, &amp; his ſacred truth.</p>
                  <p n="10">10 <hi>Reverence done at the name of Ieſus,</hi> is no ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, but an outward ſigne of our inward ſubiection to his devine Maieſty, and an apparant token of our devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Why doe they not likewiſe finde fault with kneeling, ſighing, weeping, lifting vp of eies, knocking of breaſtes, holding vp of hands vnto heaven? All which good men may vſe in Gods ſervice with great piety, though Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites doe otherwiſe.</p>
                  <p n="11">11 They are groſely ignorant if they know it not, or wilfully malicious and turbulent, if knowing it to be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, they yet oppugne <hi>the reading of the Apocriphall ſcriptures or writings in the Church. Non ad confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem fidei, ſed ad reformationem or inſtitutionem mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> as the Auncient<note n="q" place="margin">Hiero. praef. in Pro. Cypr. in Simb. Pellic. praef in Apocr. Hyper. Metho. Theol l 1. c. 6.</note> fathers ſpeake and approue. As alſo the Articles of Convocation, &amp; the Prefaces before the Apocriphal bookes in the Engliſh Bibles, doe direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhew: adding that they giue light, to the devine ſtory.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>2.</hi> Concerning Church-Miniſters.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 WEE hartely deſire <hi>that able and ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent men bee admitted into the Miniſtery. That they preach diligently, and that on the Sunday eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally.</hi> But who ſhall iudge of their ſufficiency? Or doeth not the ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy of Miniſters <hi>Suſcipere magis &amp; minus?</hi> Were the Miniſters of the Primitiue Church, al of them able to preach? Did not ſome of them preach the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell,<note n="r" place="margin">Chryſoſt. in 1. Cor. 1. Pet. Martyr. in 1. Cor. 1 Gualt. in 1. Cor. 1. Cal. in 1. Cor. 1. Bucer. in Eph. 4.</note>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:14179:16"/> and other ſome reade the Scriptures, &amp; adminiſter the Sacraments? Or hath not the vrging of that ſtrange doctrine, viz. <hi>That he is no Miniſter that cannot preach,</hi> firſt forced men to take vppon them to expound Gods word, that thereby haue brought the word of God, and the ſacred exerciſe of preaching into lamentable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, through their abſurde, ſenceleſſe, and irreligious gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſes and paraphraſes, and diſcourſes: whiles they have choſen rather ſo to doe, then to be accounted, <hi>Idol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rds, Dumbe dogges, No Miniſters,</hi> and ſuch like? Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly hath it not made the <hi>Browniſts</hi> confidently to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach vs, that our<note n="ſ" place="margin">Barrowes bookes &amp;c Perpetual go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Church. pag. 339.</note> Church is no Church, our Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments no Sacraments, our Prince and people Infidels, as not being baptiſed at all, our Chriſtian Congregations prophane multitudes, &amp;c. only becauſe ſome in the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery could not or did not preach? But in this pointe it would be conſidered eſpecia ly, firſt that it is not poſſible to have all Miniſters men of worth, til al Church-livings be very ſufficient to maintaine men of worth. Secondly that the way to invite men of beſt partes to take vppon them the Miniſtery, is not to expoſe and ſubiect that cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, to want and beggery, which in the third part of this their complaint, theſe men doe principally intend. And laſtly that howſoever theſe men doe pleaſe themſelues in their extemporary gift; yet many of them, though in ſhew very audacious, doe notwithſtanding deſerve for their groſſe ignorance, to bee blotted out of the number of preachers, truely ſo called.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Howe charitable theſe men are, that would haue men<note n="t" place="margin">Har conf. ex Helu Poſt. De Miniſt ca. 18 Agnoſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus &amp;c. Vnde ne h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reijcimus ſimplicitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp;c.</note> 
                     <hi>removed out of the Miniſtery,</hi> becauſe they cannot preach; (whereas ſome of them were intreated to take that function vpon them, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men more able could not
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14179:17"/> be gotten; and others in their yonger yeares, have beene of more ſufficiency, then now their age, ſicknes, or other infirmitie, will permit them to be:) And how indicious, that would have them <hi>to mainetaine preachers,</hi> who (for the moſt parte) haue not wherewith for to mainetaine themſelues, wee leaue to the conſideration of the wiſe. How much better hath our Church deviſed, to ſupply the defects of ſome men, in ſome places, of mean valew, by other meanes? As namely by the frequent reading of the Scriptures: A matter more<note n="u" place="margin">Zanc. Conf. obſ. in cap. 15. Aph. 10.11.</note> availeable vnto faith &amp; godlines, then the Petitioners doe imagine; and woulde be much more, if it were not brought into contempt, by their ſuggeſtions. 2 By a moſt religious and excellent<note n="x" place="margin">B. Ridley to M<hi rend="sup">•</hi>. Grindall then beyonde the ſeas. Alas that brother Knox, could not bear with our booke of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> praier, &amp;c The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons hee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth againſt the Letany, &amp;c. I do mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell howe hee can or dare a vouch the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c.</note> forme of Common praier. 3 By Sermons &amp; Homilies printed and appointed to be read, both for the confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the faith, and for reformation of manners. All which in a Church not new to be planted, but now ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and well grounded in the profeſſion of the truth; are ordinarie effectual meanes, to continue and increaſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in the true faith and feare of God. Herevnto may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the manifold proviſions in our Church, for ſermons quarterly, or more often, in thoſe Cures, where the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbents cannot preach.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 <hi>That Non-reſidency be not permitted.</hi> It is a matter of wiſe and ſound deliberation: firſt,<note n="y" place="margin">The bounds of Pariſhes are not de iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re divino.</note> what Non-reſiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie is; for many men in our Church, haue two pariſhes committed to their chardge, which both will not make one living. Againe, manie haue but one pariſh vnder them, which yet would require more then two, or tenne men to ſpeake at once to all the Congregation. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is, and long hath beene permitted, by wiſe and godly Magiſtrates, that haue given way to it, by their poſitiue
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14179:17"/> prudent lawes, as neceſſary, in ſome Caſes, in a few men, and them (generally and by intendment) of the beſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts. Thirdly that it is abſolutely vnlawful, &amp; in no<note n="z" place="margin">The anſwere to the 2. trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract.</note> ſort to be ſuffered, neither hath beene proved, nor ever will, by all the <hi>Puritanes</hi> in the Land. Fourthly, in what Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruity may he be counted an idle <hi>Non-reſident,</hi> that is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies preſent and taketh paines, in ſome part; and often in everie parte of his charge? Fiftlie, there are not more intollerable Non-reſidents in England, then ſome of thoſe, that are either included in the <hi>Thouſand</hi> afore mentioned, or that favour this their attempt: Eſpecially if they ſhall bee meaſured, by thoſe places of Scripture, which they are wont to alleage againſt <hi>Non-reſidents,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Texts be well examined. Laſtlie, it is not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, (as Church livings are now<note n="*" place="margin">To alter the precincts of pariſhes, is a matter of greater con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Abſtractor</hi> or many moe ſuch ſhallow heads can poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceave.</note> allotted) that ſimply no <hi>Non-reſidency</hi> ſhould bee permitted, and yet withall, a learned Miniſtery mainetained, Princes and Peeres of the Land attended, Colledges &amp; Cathedrall Churches continued, the Vniverſities preſent, and hope of ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in them for hereafter, preſerved, propagated, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 <hi>The Marriage of Miniſters</hi> wee doe not diſlike, but maintaine the lawfulnes thereof againſt the Church of Rome: and humblie deſire (if there be need,) that the ſupreme Magiſtrate, will adde therevnto, by his royal au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and the law of the land, ſuch farther ſtrength and confirmation, as ſhall ſeeme fit to his high wiſedome.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 We know of <hi>no Subſcription that is vrged, which is not agreeable to law,</hi> required by the orders of our Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, neceſſary in a Chriſtian Common-wealth, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for the Church of God, approueable by all iudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous learned men, and diſliked of none, but a few folke,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14179:18"/> that are overmuch addicted to their own opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Who notwithſtanding where<note n="a" place="margin">The lawes &amp; ſtatuts of Gen. In the forme of Oth, which the Miniſters receiue, Sect 2 Beza in vita Cal pag 910.</note> they beare the ſway, it is worth the Conſideration, how ſtrictly they tie all them that wil liue among them, to the obſervation of their Church go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. And in truth, (ſo the things in themſelues bee not intollerable) better ſo, then that which is heere pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed. For the not vrging of a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>formity in Church diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, is to ſet open the high way to all diſorder and Confuſion.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>3. <hi>Concerning Church mainetenance.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1 <hi>THat Biſhops leave their Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dams.</hi> In caſe ſome of the auncient revenew might bee reſtored to their Biſhoprickes, hee were vtterly vnworthie to be a Biſhop, that would deſire a <hi>Commendam.</hi> But, as now the moſt of them are impaired, to take away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all Biſhops al manner of <hi>Commendams,</hi> is (in truth) to tie the Kings hands, that he ſhal not be able, though he would, (and where he will not, no <hi>Commendam</hi> can be given;) to make his moſt faithfull ſervants, or other men of beſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert in the Miniſtery, able to mainetaine their places and callings, by his Maieſties favour, and gracious diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; when otherwiſe their Biſhoprickes are not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſo to doe. So as if it bee well wayed, they doe not ſo much intend in this particular to impoveriſh ſome fewe Biſhops, as indeede vtterly to overthrow them, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally to reſtraine the Kings prerogatiue.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Of the ſame nature is that which followeth. For no man except hee bee the Kings Chaplaine may holde <hi>Three benefices with Cure;</hi> and thoſe of his Highnes own gifte. So that here alſo they deſire to limit the Kings fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14179:18"/> Againe it is not knowne, that there be fiue in al this land, that hold three ſuch benefices. And then what good dealing is this in the Petitioners, to make the worlde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, that it is a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon fault, which is ſcarſe to be found in a few?</p>
                  <p n="3">3 <hi>Their diſpoſing of Impropriations,</hi> doeth notably bewray their lacke of<note n="c" place="margin">The Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical diſcipl. pag. 114.</note> Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience; their litle loue to lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and religion; their temporizing and fitting their motions to the Laities good liking. For who ſeeth not that it would bee the certaine overthrow and vtter ruine of <hi>Biſhoprickes, Colledges, and Cathedrall Churches;</hi> if their <hi>Impropriations ſhould bee demiſed to the Vicars or Curates the Incumbents at the old rent,</hi> without fine, without im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouement? Againe who be they, and how many, that by this meanes would be provided for? A few, and thoſe the meaneſt of the Cleargy. But the inconveniences that would hereof enſue, are very many, &amp; intollerable. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we reſerue that diſcourſe, to a fit opportunity. On the otherſide, who doth not know, that for a Lay-man to hold an Impropriation <hi>(which is a Tith)</hi> is originallie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, and cleane contrary to their firſt inſtitution? Yet theſe men in all their puritie, zeale, &amp; conſcience, can co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent themſelues, and their preaching Incumbents, vvith the ſeventh parte onely of an Impropriation, in a Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans fee.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 Are theſe al, or the beſt meanes, that <hi>a Thouſande me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſuch as they would be reputed,</hi> can propoſe to his High<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes for the bettering of the Church maintenance? If we might know that it would ſtand with his Maieſties good liking, and ſhould not be imputed vnto vs as a breach of duetie; It were very poſſible, that the men whom they ſo much contemne, woulde bee able to propoſe ſome other
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14179:19"/> courſe for the bettring of the Church maintenance, with out the alteration or iniurie of any other ſtate.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>4 <hi>Concerning Church Diſcipline.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1 VNder the name of their <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> we haue bin heretofore taught by theſe men to vnderſtand, <hi>The kingdome of Chriſt vpon earth: A thing of no leſſe importance then the</hi>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">Eccleſ Diſci- pag 13 T C Epiſt to the Church of England.</note> 
                     <hi>Goſpell of Christ Ieſus; An eſſentiall part of the Goſpell: A matter of faith to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved vpon paine of damnation; An eſſentiall marke of the true Church: without the which our Church was no Church our faith no faith, our Goſpell no Goſpell, &amp;c.</hi> And it is now come to be ſo indifferent, as that it may bee adminiſtred accordingly; <hi>Or els at the least, that theſe enormities may be redreſsed?</hi> Will it now ſuffer ſuch an <hi>Or elſe, at the least?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Were we perſwaded, that their <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> their <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery,</hi> the life and being of their <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> were indeed of Chriſtes inſtitution; were we perſwaded it were <hi>a part of Gods word, an eſſentiall part of his word;</hi> coulde wee be contented to be without it? Could we content our ſelues to liue any where, but vnder it? Would we not redeeme it with much perill and paine? With certaine loſſe? And that willingly?</p>
                  <p>But the experience that his moſt excellent Maieſtie hath had, of the manifolde miſchiefes and miſeries, that attend their pretended Diſcipline, doth make them not dare to ſpeake plainly for it. They therefore faulter in ſeeking to obtaine that, which yet in hart they do affect, and ſpecially deſire.</p>
                  <p>But to theſe <hi>Enormities;</hi> theſe heinous <hi>Enormities.</hi> Is
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14179:19"/> it not well, that nowe at length, theſe quick-ſighted men, can eſpie no fowler <hi>enormities</hi> in our Church governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Enormities.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 <hi>THAT Exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication come not forth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of Lay perſons.</hi> Firſt, it may truely be ſaid, that though it did come forth vnder the name of a Chauncelour, or a Comiſſarie; yet came it not forth vnder the name of Lay-perſons. For a Chauncelour or a Comiſſary, is not a Lay-man in this caſe: The ordinary and he are but <hi>Vnus iudex.</hi> Or rather, whatſoever the Chauncelour doth in this behalfe, hee doth it in the auctority of the Ordinary, according to the power that is committed vnto him. A thing not vnuſual in the Civill ſtate: wherein the Lord-Chauncelour doth diſpoſe of many thinges, which are Originally in the Crowne; and againe, writeth <hi>Teſte meipſo</hi> vnto manie particulars, that never paſſe by bill aſſigned.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, no Lay-Chauncelour or Comiſſary what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever doth at any time exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate any man; or ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h out in his <hi>owne name</hi> any exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication. But this is the practiſe of the Church of England. In<note n="e" place="margin">Conſt. Ecc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 1597 cap d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Exceſt circ. Excom. ref<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> the ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſuring of notorious &amp; more grievous crimes, the Arch biſhop, the Biſhop, the Deane, the Arch-deacon, or a Proben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a Prieſt, pronounceth the ſentence of Exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication in his owne perſon. And in matters of leſſe offence, as contumacy in not appearing and the like, the <hi>Vicar generall, Officiall, or Comiſſary,</hi> that is not in holie orders, houldeth this courſe. Firſt vpon knowledge and examinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the cauſe, he adiudgeth the party worthy
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14179:20"/> to be excommunicate; then the Miniſter (aſſociated vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him by expreſſe authority from the Ordinarie) doeth pronounce the ſentence of excommunication againſt him; Laſtly the Chancelour ſendeth to the <hi>Pastor</hi> of the pariſh, where that party dwelleth, requiring him publik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to declare the ſaide party to bee a perſon excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated by the ſentence of the Miniſter his aſſociate. And all this, according to the forme of the Articles ſet forth by her Maieſties auctoritie Ann. 1597.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, are not theſe excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <hi>Enormity makers,</hi> that can finde ſuch an <hi>Enormitie</hi> in the <hi>Name of a Lay-man,</hi> (in whoſe name notwithſtanding the excommunication never co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth forth,) when yet if it did come forth in his name, the nature of the thing it ſelfe is ſuch, as iuſtly can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be reproved? They are not ignorant, that excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication doth proceed as is afore-ſaid; if not in the name, yet in the Autoritie and Iuriſdiction of the Biſhoppe, or ſome other chiefe Clergy-man, to whom the power of the Keies doth belong, and vnto vvhom the Church of England hath aſſigned the execution of that part of our Diſcipline. Who if they vſe the adviſe and Miniſterie of a wiſe and religious Civilian, in decreeing who is to bee excommunicate; (Whervpon thoſe<note n="f" place="margin">Perpetuall govern of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hu. pag. 320.</note> ontward penalties do enſue, which attend the auctority, and follow the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of excommunication in this Church &amp; Common wealth:) how doth that in any wiſe violate Chriſts Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution as touching excommunication?</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, if the Diſcipline they long for, were once on foote among vs, wee ſhould then heare tell of certaine <hi>Lay-parſons</hi> that ought to haue a principall hand in their Excommunications. Thus as they are weake in Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for matter of Learning in this point, not being able
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14179:20"/> to reſolue of any thing in certaine; ſo are they as partiall in preſcribing their plottes for matter of practiſe; whiles they reproue that in others, which in themſelues they do allow. Except peradventure they will tell vs, (and wee muſt needs beleeue them) that their <hi>Lay-Elders</hi> become Clergy me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>ipſo facto;</hi> becauſe they are of their Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; and haue voices (according to their learning) in theſe Eccleſiaſticall cenſures.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 <hi>That none bee excommunicated for</hi>
                     <note n="g" place="margin">The order of Excom. &amp;c in the Chur. of Scot. Print. Iune 1571. Cap 4. Thus any ſmall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, may iuſtly deſerve Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt &amp; diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of the offendor.</note> 
                     <hi>trifles and twelue pennie matters.</hi> They are not. Contempte is then the greater, when the matter wherein they ſhewe their contempt, is of leſſer valew: As contrariwiſe, obedience is then more commendable, when it is ſeene in a matter of greater difficulty. But theſe men are ſo accuſtomed to diſobedience, that they account it but a trifle; And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore calumniate vs and our diſcipline, as if with vs men were excommunicated ſo trifles, when (in truth) they are cenſured for their contempt.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 <hi>That none be excommunicated without conſent of his Paſtor. VVithout conſent,</hi> is a captious tearme. For in our vnderſtanding, the Miniſter of the pariſh doth give his conſent, when he publiſheth the excommunication; as alſo when hee doth certifie what hee hath done in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing of the ſame. And this manner of conſent, wee take to be ſufficient, and as much as is requiſite in a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate <hi>Paſtor</hi> that hath no Iuriſdiction.</p>
                  <p>But what is it that theſe men do meane? Would they (thinke you) that every Paſtor ſhould haue a Negatiue in the excommunicating of his pariſhioners? Vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly they would. Therby intending the vtter overthrow of the preſent Church government, and in ſteed thereof the ſetting vp of a <hi>Presbitery</hi> in every pariſh. Or rather,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14179:21"/> that which is worſe (if worſe may be) the enabling of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very particular Paſtour to excommunicate by himſelfe<note n="h" place="margin">Perpetuall governement of the Church pag. 321.</note> alone.</p>
                  <p>Except peradventure they wil ſay, that the particular <hi>Paſtor</hi> ought to be ioyned in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion with the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celour. And then beholde what would enſue. On the Miniſter, a world of troubles: he muſt be ſent for as oft as any of his pariſh is preſented, he muſt attend the hearing and debating of the whole cauſe; he muſt bee preſent as oft as the Chauncelour ſitteth, as long as the matter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth: to his great travaile and paines, his exceſſiue charge, and the cauſleſſe neglecte of his calling. On the otherſide, if this Miniſter wil be wilful, and in fine diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from the Chauncelour in opinion; then is al the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour loſt; the Iudge hath ſpent his skill and care in vaine, and the Biſhops Conſiſtory muſt downe to the ground: either <hi>Paſtor</hi> muſt prevaile, or nothing muſt be done; To the intollerable hinderance of Iuſtice, and exceſſiue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment of the plaintife. Theſe and the like, are the well adviſed Propoſitions, whereof there is ſtore in their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline. By which it doth ſufficiently appeare, that as yet it is not throughly refined.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 <hi>Extorting of vnreaſonable fees,</hi> who approveth? Who diſliketh not? Who would not haue it redreſſed, in any that offend? Beſides there are very<note n="i" place="margin">Conſtit. Eccl. 1597. cap. de Foedis quae off. Eccleſ.</note> ſevere lawes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready made in that behalfe.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 <hi>Farming out of Iuriſdictions and Registers places,</hi> though we commende it not, nor greatly like of it; yet it is of it ſelfe a matter indifferent; neither good nor ill, but as it is vſed.</p>
                  <p n="6">6 The reſtraint of <hi>Marriage at certaine times</hi> (falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called a Popiſh Canon) vvas<note n="k" place="margin">Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſil. Laodi. Can. 2.</note> auncientlie vſed in the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14179:21"/> Church of God; &amp; being rightly vnderſtood, is now co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable in this of ours.</p>
                  <p n="7">7 The <hi>Long-ſomnes of Suits in Eccleſiaſtical Courts,</hi> is a matter of fact, not of Conſtitution; nor is the fault of the Courte, nor of the Iudge neceſſarily (as theſe men would ſeeme to imply,) but ſometime error in pleading, ſometime the intricatenes of the cauſe, ſomtime the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeneſſe of the Clyent, ſometime the cunning of the Proctors, are the occaſion that ſuites depend long. And when al is ſaid, that they can ſay, this is none other fault, then is incident to the courſe of Iuſtice at the Common Law; and might befall their Conſiſtory, or a better and more equal kinde of trial.</p>
                  <p n="8">8 <hi>The Oth ex officio,</hi> is vſed as it ought, by men of place, of wiſedome, and experience; by men of religion, learning, and conſcience. Vnto whom the authority to adminiſter it as occaſion is offered doeth iuſtly belong, not by ſpecial Commiſſion only, but by the laws of this land, by the two Laws Canon and Civil; and by the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dry Examples of the word of God: as that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy &amp; learned Deane of the Arches <hi>(the ornament &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of his profeſsion in his time)</hi> in his iudicious<note n="l" place="margin">The Apolog. 2 part Cha. 9. and ſo forth to the end of the ſame.</note> Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy of certain proceedings in Courts Eccleſiaſtical, doth proue at large.</p>
                  <p n="9">9 <hi>Licenſes for Marriage without Banes,</hi> are moſt <hi>cautiouſly graunted;</hi> and that vpon<note n="m" place="margin">Conſt. Eccl. 1597 cap. de moder. Indulg</note> ſevere puniſhmente to enſue, if ſo be the Conſtitution be violated. But what wil ſatiſfie theſe men, who thus intimate vnto his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that there is rigor in the former point, and negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in this, when as al moderation and carefulnes is v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in them both?</p>
                  <p>And are not theſe <hi>heynous enormities?</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:14179:22"/>
               <head>Their Concluſion.</head>
               <p>THe idle vaunt that the Petitioners make of <hi>being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſhew that theſe and other ſuch abuſes</hi> (as they call them) <hi>remaining and practiſed in the Church of England, are not agreeable to the Scriptures,</hi> doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to be the more ridiculous; becauſe they haue paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed over in deepe ſilence many learned<note n="n" place="margin">The perpet. gover. of Chri. Chur. A ſurvey of the pret. holy diſc. The anſwer to the Abſtract. The Apol. of certaine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in Cour. Eccle. A treatiſe of Eccleſ. Diſcip De Preſbyt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> nova. &amp;c. De div. Miniſt. Evan. grad. &amp;c The Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance. Querimonia Eccleſiae. The 5. bookes of the laws of Eccleſ. polit.</note> Tracts publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed long ſince, wherein their vaine fancies, and illiterate obiections are refuted at large. If notwithſtanding they wil yet venture to vvrite, it vvil bee anſwered; If they wil needes argue and diſpute, there are ready that wil either ſatiſfie them, or by argument ſilence them. And were it not in regard that we would not ſeeme as vndutiful in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting, as they haue beene in the offering of this Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendge: it is the thing we would vrge, &amp; inſtantly entreat, that theſe matters might be debated betweene vs in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. But in the mean time, what motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are theſe for the Reformers to make vnto a moſt prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Prince in his ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led &amp; peaceable government; who for many years, hath had trial in that his other kingdome, of their prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; &amp; in this alſo hath ſeene the gracious effectes vnder her Maieſties late happy Raigne, of that Church diſcipline, which they would ruinate and ouerthrow.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>God hath appointed his Maieſtye vnto this kingdome.</hi> It is true; and wee magnifie the goodneſſe of God for it, and congratulate his Highnes in the proſperous poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it, from the ground of our heartes. But that God hath appointed him to this kingdome <hi>for ſuch a purpoſe as they conceite;</hi> what ſpirit of divination is in them, that they ſhould foreſpeake it? Nay rather, ſeeing almighty God hath ordained him as the great Phyſition (next and immediatelie vnder himſelfe,) to take care of the body politique both of this Church and Common-wealth; he
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14179:22"/> will ſurely cure ſuch diſeaſes, as theſe men are ſicke of. (For turbulent and diſcontented humors, whether in Papiſt, or in Puritane are like to breede very daungerous diſeaſes in a civill State:) And not bee perſwaded (as they fondly imagine) by ſuch ſuggeſtions as theſe, to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that ſtate of the Church, which is acceptable to God, honourable to his Highnes, comfortable to many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Miniſters, the Nurſe of good learning, admirable to ſtrangers, approved by our<note n="*" place="margin">The letters that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Beza hath written to the ArchB. of C: that nowe is:</note> Oppoſites, envied of our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, diſtaſtfull vnto none, but ſuch as know neither how to rule, nor how to obey.</p>
               <p>The very names of <hi>Puniſhmentes</hi> are vnpleaſant in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede; but the thinges themſelues are neceſſary ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, and their effects good and profitable for preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the whole; howſoever the induring of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, may be grievous in the particular. And he that will indifferentlie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider the true cauſes of the correctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s here me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned; ſhall haue iuſt cauſe to approue the Iuſtice,<note n="*" place="margin">Conſpiracy for pretended Reformation.</note> &amp; comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the mildnes, that hath bin vſed towards this ſort of men.</p>
               <p>As for that clauſe of <hi>Mens traditions,</hi> it is too too odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; &amp; would imply ſuperſtition or popery to be in ſome of them. But how vainely, and how iniuriouſty; hath in ſome ſort bin heretofore declared.</p>
               <p>That other of <hi>beeing preiudiciall to note but thoſe that ſeeke their owne &amp;c.</hi> is as iniurious to all the reſt of the Miniſters of this land. Be we the men that are ſo addicted to <hi>our owne Quiet, Credite, and Commoditie in the world?</hi> Where then be the fruits of our covetouſnes, the effects of our ambition, the markes of our idlenes? VVe be the men, that in the teſtimony of a good Conſcience, for the repelling of ſuch a malicious contumely, &amp; ſlaunderous reproach, may truly ſay: We put not out our mony to V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury; we deteſt al filthy lucre; we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taine our ſelues with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14179:23"/> our Vocations; we forſake not our holy callings; we o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit not to labour in our ſeverall chardges; we ſuſtaine the places of great labour travaile and expenſe, wee neglect not in publike, in private, in word, in writing, at home &amp; abroad, to put to ſilence, and ſtop the mouth of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Adverſary, which theſe men haue enlarged againſt vs, and our moſt holy faith.</p>
               <p>To conclude, the thinge they ſeeke is <hi>ſo preiudiciall,</hi> both to the Civil ſtate in general, and in particular, to ſo many of the very beſt of the Miniſtery; that if it ſhoulde take effect, (but God of his mercy, &amp; the Kings moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Maieſty in his Chriſtian wiſedome, will not ſuffer it) it would breede a ſtrange alteration in the One; and in the Other it would for the preſent, not only impoveriſh vs, and our Vniverſities, but make both them and vs, and the whole Cleargie very baſe and contemtible in the eies of our own people, as alſo a By-word &amp; a skorne to our neighbour Nations; And for ſucceeding ages, it would cut off all hope of a learned Miniſtery, and of that grounded learning, which as yet is, and heretofore hath beene, the glorie and honour of this kingdome.</p>
               <p>For manifeſtation of this point, looke vpon the face of all the reformed Churches in the world; and whereſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the deſire of theſe Petitioners doth take place, be it duly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered; <hi>Firſt,</hi> how wel their proceedings do ſuite with the ſtate of a <hi>Monarchy;</hi> And <hi>then,</hi> how poverty on the one ſide, &amp; lacke of learning on the other, doth creep vpon the whole Clergy in thoſe Dominions.</p>
               <p>As to the firſt: woulde it not beſeeme the ſuperemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent auctority and Regal perſon of a <hi>King,</hi> to be himſelfe confined within the limites of ſome particular pariſh; &amp; then to ſubiect his ſoveraigne power, to the pure Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lical ſimplicity, of an over-ſwaying &amp; al-commaunding
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14179:23"/> Presbitery? Would it not doe him much good, in a time of neede, that his people ſhould be rooted and grounded in this truth, viz. That his meeke and humble Clergie, have power <hi>to bind their King in chaines, &amp; their Prince in lincks of iro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?</hi> That is, (in their learning) to cenſure him, to enioine him penance, to excommunicate him? yea (in caſe they ſee cauſe) to proceede againſt him, as a Tyrant?</p>
               <p>We ſpeake not heere of other points, as namely, that all appeales in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall, (and what doe they not make Eccleſiaſticall?) muſt finallie lye, not vnto the Prince, but vnto the Aſſembly Provinciall; That they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the ſupreme Magiſtrate, not <hi>potestatem iuris,</hi> but only <hi>facti;</hi> while they make him, the maintainer of their proceedings, but no commander in them. Theſe and the like, are but petty Abridgments of the Praerogatiue Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, while yet the <hi>King</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">T.C. l. 1. pag. 180.</note> 
                  <hi>ſubmits his ſcepter vnto the ſcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Chriſt, and lickes the duſt of the Churches feete.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neither may it be truly ſaid, that theſe are onely Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culations. There are ſome of High place yet alive, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſome are dead, that haue felte the ſmarte heereof in their owne experience, and haue ſeene the worſt of all this put in wofull execution.</p>
               <p>As to the ſecond. Do we not ſee it at this day verified among them, which hath beene ſo often truly ſaide, &amp; as often vnadviſedly denied, that <hi>Hones alit artes;</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe, where due reward of learning and liberal main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the Miniſtery, is fraudulently impaired, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuriouſly taken away,<note n="b" place="margin">Eccleſiaſ. diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipl. pag. 114.</note> there Religion and learning come to decay? There Atheiſme and Barbariſme &amp; Confuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt needes enſue? It is to apparent, that as the reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes of thoſe Churches haue bin embeazeled by men of corrupt mindes, which ſaide in their hearts, as it is in the Pſalme,<note place="margin">Pſal. 83.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Let vs take to our ſelues the houſes of God in
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14179:24"/> poſſeſsion:</hi> ſo the remainder of that grounded learning, which was bredde vp in former times, is nowe through ſucceſſion of time, almoſt cleane morne out: <q>Nec bonatam ſequitur, quam bona prima fuit.</q> Inſomuch, that there is neither ſufficient maintena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in thoſe parts for any ſtore of excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t learned men, nor yet many men brought vp among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this laſt reforming age, worthy of that wonted honorable maintenance.</p>
               <p>God knowes we ſpeake not this with a detracting ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, but with griefe of hart: to ſee the ruines of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery in particular, &amp; generally of al profound learning in other reformed Churches. As likewiſe to ſtirre vp this whole Nation, to a thankefull acknowledgement of that ſingular bleſſing in this behalfe, which God of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hath longe, and yet doth continue, vnto vs of this Realme. And with all, to put to ſilence the malicious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude of thoſe evill men, which looking vpon vs and this Church, through the coloured glaſſe of their praeiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s; can ſee nothing among vs, <hi>but defects &amp; deformities, and abuſes, and Enormities,</hi> and the like. And therefore in their high diſcretion, would haue vs reduced &amp; made conformable, to the calamities of other places.</p>
               <p>Wheras (in truth, if we ſhal bring backe the eies of our minds fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> forraine parts, &amp; indifferently (without either detractio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or flattery) take notice of the preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſtate of this Church &amp; Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>-wealth; we ſhal eaſily diſcerne, that it were an incomparable happines for them, if all that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the truth as it is in Chriſt Ieſus, were in our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p>We ſhal ſee, how that our Church governme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, is du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubordinat vnto the ſupreme civil ſtate, &amp; withal doth mightily ſupport the ſame. That our Reverend Prelates (me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſingular worth, not to be matched in any one ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome) though preferred vnto highes roomes; do yet co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14179:24"/> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues within ſuch bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, as preſerue that eſtate, from creeping to any Papal corruptions. That our inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Clergy, by their godly &amp; painful labours in their Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, haue bin, &amp; are the moſt effectuall meanes, to ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle the tranquillity of this land; by inducing mens mindes vnto piety towards God, Loyalty to their King, &amp; Civill honeſty amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues. That our people generally, (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting ſome few Maleco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tents of al ſorts, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wee leaue to the mercy of the Magiſtrate) are invred vnto peace, accuſtomed to ſubiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, deteſt diſloyalty, &amp; with al ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critie yeeld their obedience vnto their Soveraigne.</p>
               <p>That the Colledges, the Cathedral Churches, the Biſhops, &amp; other Miniſters of this Land, haue yet remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, (yet, after the many &amp; great ſpoiles of this Church; which notwithſtanding,<note place="margin">Saravia de ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegijs, ca 9.</note> never proſpered vvith the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that got the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; but were as Ruſt to the reſt of their ſilver &amp; their gold, or as a Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ker, that fretted out themſelues, their poſterity, or their poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s:) that yet there is remai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, more competent, &amp; ſufficient maintena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce; more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable &amp; honorable encourageme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there are, vnto all other the reformed churches in Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e.</p>
               <p>That anſwerable thervnto, (to ſtop that mouth of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, which is wont to traduce vs, for <hi>a dumb, vnlearned, Idoll Miniſtery</hi>) there are at this day, more learned men in this Land, in this one Kingdome; then are to be found among al the Miniſters of the Religion, in <hi>France, Flaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Germany, Poleland, Denmarke, Geneva, Scotland;</hi> or (to ſpeake in a word) in all Europe beſides.</p>
               <p>Which yet, may not iuſtly be imputed vnto vs for va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. The Apoſtle that knew how to be abaſed,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9. 2 Cor. 12.</note> &amp; to make himſelfe of no reputation; yet whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the impeaching of his perſonall giftes, was abuſed to the diſgrace of his calling: did without either arroga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy or folly, giue his Detractors
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:14179:25"/> plainly &amp; roundly to vnderſtand, that he was not inferior to the chiefe Apoſtles; nay that he labored more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they al; &amp; ſo by his own iuſt defence &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation, did free himſelfe, his worth, &amp; his Vocation, from their baſe and odious imputations. In a like caſe (we doubt not) a truth may be averred of our ſelues, even by our ſelues, without any oſtentation at all; when it is ſo iniuriouſly impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and troden vnder foote, to the high diſhonor of God, the diſgrace of his Goſpel, and to the ſlander of this moſt Chriſtian Common-wealth. Yea the rich mercies, that God hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued vnto vs, now theſe fiue &amp; forty years, ought to repleniſh our harts with ioy; ſo that our lippes ſhould breake forth with thankfulnes and ſing,<note place="margin">Pſal. 47.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Non fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit taliter omni nationi;</hi> neither haue the Regions round about vs, beene made partakers of the like bleſſings.</p>
               <p>Now the Father of Mercies, and God of al Conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, enlarge the wiſe and vnderſtanding hart, of our thrice noble King, noble in birth, noble in wiſedome, noble in al manner of good learning; aſſiſt him ever with his holy ſpirit, the ſpirit of Counſaile, of ſanctificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; of truth: make him admirable in the ſwaying of this Scepter as was <hi>Salomon</hi> in al the world, as long as hee walked in the firſt waies of his father <hi>David:</hi> That ſo hee maye longe weare this mortal Crowne, in al abundaunce of Piety, Peace, &amp; Proſperity; &amp; hereafter obtaine that immortal Crowne, that Chriſt hath purchaſed for them, <hi>which by continuance in well doing, ſeeke glory and honour and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14179:25"/>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
